<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Solid Geometry Tutorial</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <h1>Solid Geometry Tutorial</h1>
    <h3>Building teapots with Commons Geometry</h3>
    <section name="Contents" id="toc">
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="#introduction">Introduction</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#getting-started">Getting Started</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#body">Creating the body</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Introduction" id="introduction">
      <p>
      <em>Commons Geometry</em> contains a number of methods for manipulating solid, 3D dimensional figures. 
      These geometric figures can be combined in various ways to produce new figures. In this tutorial,
      we will explore these features by using them to construct a 3D model of a teapot from scratch. The image
      below shows the result of our efforts. The final code for this tutorial can be found in the 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-examples/commons-geometry-examples-tutorials/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/examples/tutorials/teapot/TeapotBuilder.html">
      TeapotBuilder</a> class.
      </p>
      <p>
      <strong>NOTE:</strong> Unless otherwise noted, all images used in this tutorial have been rendered 
      using <a href="https://www.blender.org/" target="_blank">Blender</a>.
      </p> 
      <img src="../images/tutorials/teapot/teapot-final.png" />
    </section>
    
    <section name="Getting Started" id="getting-started">
      <p>
      The first step we will take on our journey is the creation of a class encapsulating our teapot-construction
      logic, aptly named <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-examples/commons-geometry-examples-tutorials/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/examples/tutorials/teapot/TeapotBuilder.html">TeapotBuilder</a>.
      The constructor will accept only a single argument: an instance of 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/core/precision/DoublePrecisionContext.html">DoublePrecisionContext</a>.
      This is a ubiquitous type in <em>Commons Geometry</em> and is used to provide a method of comparing
      floating point numbers without being susceptible to small floating point errors introduced during computations.
      Typically, users of <em>Commons Geometry</em> will construct a single instance of this type for use by multiple
      objects throughout an entire operation, or even an entire application. Since we don't want our lowly class to 
      assume such a heavy responsibility, we will simply accept a <span class="code">DoublePrecisionContext</span> in
      the constructor.
      </p>
      <source>
public class TeapotBuilder {

    private final DoublePrecisionContext precision;

    public TeapotBuilder(final DoublePrecisionContext precision) {
        this.precision = precision;
    }
}</source>
      <p>
      Next, we will create a stub method for our teapot-building code. We will fill in this method as we work through
      the tutorial.
      </p>
      <source>
public RegionBSPTree3D buildTeapot() {
    RegionBSPTree3D teapot = RegionBSPTree3D.empty();
    
    // TODO: actually build a teapot here
    
    return null;
}</source>
      <p>
      We have chosen the <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/threed/RegionBSPTree3D.html">RegionBSPTree3D</a>
      type for both the construction of the teapot geometry as well as the return value. This is the primary type
      in <em>Commons Geometry</em> for manipulating solid geometries. (There are similar such types for each space and 
      dimension supported by the library, for example 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/twod/RegionBSPTree2D.html">RegionBSPTree2D</a>
      for 2D Euclidean space and 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/spherical/twod/RegionBSPTree2S.html">RegionBSPTree2S</a>
      for 2D spherical space.) This type uses a 
      <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_space_partitioning">binary space partitioning (BSP) tree</a>
      to represent arbitrary regions of space, including regions of infinite size. This is accomplished by recursively
      dividing a space in two by partitioning planes (or, more generally, "hyperplanes"). The spaces on either side of
      the planes are then given the labels "inside" or "outside". A region is then composed of all of the "inside" portions
      of the BSP tree.
      </p>
      <p>
      A major benefit of using BSP trees to represent regions is that it allows us to perform boolean operations such
      as union, intersection, difference, and xor on arbitrary regions. This is exactly how we will build our teapot geometry:
      by using the BSP tree boolean operations to combine simpler shapes into the final product.
      </p>
      <p>
      Before constructing our first geometry, we need to handle one more bit of housekeeping, namely, how to view our
      work. The easiest way to do this is to export our geometries using a common 3D file format, such as STL, and view the
      model in a 3D modeling program. I enjoy working with <a href="https://www.blender.org/" target="_blank">Blender</a>
      so that is the modeling program I have chosen to use for this tutorial. However any program able to load and display
      3D models should work. To create our geometry files, we will use the 3D file writing capabilities built in to <em>Commons Geometry</em>
      and accessible through the 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/io/euclidean/threed/IO3D.html">IO3D</a>
      convenience class. See the
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/io/euclidean/threed/GeometryFormat3D.html">GeometryFormat3D</a>
      enum for a list of supported file formats.
      </p>
      <source>
TeapotBuilder builder = new TeapotBuilder(precision);

RegionBSPTree3D teapot = builder.buildTeapot();

IO3D.write(teapot, Paths.get("teapot.stl"));</source>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Creating the body" id="body">
    </section>
  </body>
</document>