<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Solid Geometry Tutorial</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <h1>Solid Geometry Tutorial</h1>
    <h3>Building teapots with Commons Geometry</h3>
    <section name="Contents" id="toc">
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="#introduction">Introduction</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#getting-started">Getting Started</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#parts">Building the parts</a>
          <ul>
            <li><a href="#body">Body</a></li>
            <li><a href="#lid">Lid</a></li>
            <li><a href="#handle">Handle</a></li>
            <li><a href="#spout">Spout</a></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#putting-it-together">Putting it all together</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Introduction" id="introduction">
      <p>
      <em>Commons Geometry</em> contains a number of methods for manipulating solid, 3D dimensional figures. 
      These geometric figures can be combined in various ways to produce new figures. In this tutorial,
      we will explore these features by using them to construct a 3D model of a teapot from scratch. The image
      below shows the result of our efforts. The final code for this tutorial can be found in the 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-examples/commons-geometry-examples-tutorials/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/examples/tutorials/teapot/TeapotBuilder.html">
      TeapotBuilder</a> class.
      </p>
      <p>
      <strong>NOTE:</strong> Unless otherwise noted, all images used in this tutorial have been rendered 
      using <a href="https://www.blender.org/" target="_blank">Blender</a>.
      </p> 
      <img src="../images/tutorials/teapot/teapot-final.png" />
    </section>
    
    <section name="Getting Started" id="getting-started">
      <p>
      The first step we will take on our journey is the creation of a class encapsulating our teapot-construction
      logic, aptly named <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-examples/commons-geometry-examples-tutorials/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/examples/tutorials/teapot/TeapotBuilder.html">TeapotBuilder</a>.
      The constructor will accept only a single argument: an instance of 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/core/precision/DoublePrecisionContext.html">DoublePrecisionContext</a>.
      This is a ubiquitous type in <em>Commons Geometry</em> and is used to provide a method of comparing
      floating point numbers without being susceptible to small floating point errors introduced during computations.
      Typically, users of <em>Commons Geometry</em> will construct a single instance of this type for use by multiple
      objects throughout an entire operation, or even an entire application. Since we don't want our class to 
      assume such a heavy responsibility, we will simply accept a <span class="code">DoublePrecisionContext</span> in
      the constructor.
      </p>
      <source>
public class TeapotBuilder {

    private final DoublePrecisionContext precision;

    public TeapotBuilder(final DoublePrecisionContext precision) {
        this.precision = precision;
    }
}</source>
      <p>
      Next, we will create a stub method for our teapot-building code. We will fill in this method as we work through
      the tutorial.
      </p>
      <source>
public RegionBSPTree3D buildTeapot() {
    RegionBSPTree3D teapot = RegionBSPTree3D.empty();
    
    // TODO: actually build a teapot here
    
    return teapot;
}</source>
      <p>
      We have chosen the <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/threed/RegionBSPTree3D.html">RegionBSPTree3D</a>
      type for both the construction of the teapot geometry as well as the return value. This is the primary type
      in <em>Commons Geometry</em> for manipulating solid geometries. (There are similar such types for each space and 
      dimension supported by the library, such as
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/twod/RegionBSPTree2D.html">RegionBSPTree2D</a>
      for 2D Euclidean space and 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/spherical/twod/RegionBSPTree2S.html">RegionBSPTree2S</a>
      for 2D spherical space.) This type uses a 
      <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_space_partitioning">binary space partitioning (BSP) tree</a>
      to represent arbitrary regions of space, including regions of infinite size. This is accomplished by recursively
      dividing a space in two by partitioning planes (or "hyperplanes", to use the more general term). The spaces on either side of
      the planes are then given the labels "inside" or "outside". A region is then composed of all of the "inside" portions
      of the BSP tree.
      </p>
      <p>
      A major benefit of using BSP trees to represent regions is that it allows us to perform boolean operations such
      as union, intersection, difference, and xor on arbitrary regions. This is exactly how we will build our teapot geometry:
      by using the BSP tree boolean operations to combine simpler shapes into the final product.
      </p>
      <p>
      Before constructing our first geometry, we need to handle one more bit of housekeeping, namely, how to view our
      work. The easiest way to do this is to export our geometries using a common 3D file format, such as STL, and view the
      model in a 3D modeling program. I enjoy working with <a href="https://www.blender.org/" target="_blank">Blender</a>
      so that is the modeling program I have chosen to use for this tutorial. However any program able to load and display
      3D models should work. To create our geometry files, we will use the 3D file writing capabilities built in to <em>Commons Geometry</em>
      and accessible through the 
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/io/euclidean/threed/IO3D.html">IO3D</a>
      convenience class. See the
      <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/io/euclidean/threed/GeometryFormat3D.html">GeometryFormat3D</a>
      enum for a list of supported file formats.
      </p>
      <source>
TeapotBuilder builder = new TeapotBuilder(precision);

RegionBSPTree3D teapot = builder.buildTeapot();

IO3D.write(teapot, Paths.get("teapot.stl"));</source>
    <p>
    With this bit of code place, we can now run our <span class="code">TeapotBuilder</span>, load the <var>teapot.stl</var>
    file in our 3D modeling program, and see our first pass at a teapot!
    </p>
    <img src="../images/tutorials/teapot/teapot-first-pass.png" />
    <p>
    Well, that is a bit underwhelming to say the least. The <span class="code">RegionBSPTree3D</span> instance that we 
    are returning from our <span class="code">TeapotBuilder</span> is completely empty so there is nothing to look at.
    We'll start adding content next.
    </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Building the Parts" id="parts">
      <p>
      Now that we have a basic code skeleton in place, we can begin constructing the various parts of our teapot. We 
      will have four main parts: 1) the body, 2) the lid, 3) the handle, and 4) the spout. We will create
      private methods in our <span class="code">TeapotBuilder</span> for each part.
      </p>
      
      <subsection name="The Body" id="body">
        <p>
        We will start on the teapot body by creating a new private method named <span class="code">buildBody</span> and 
        referencing it in the primary <span class="code">buildTeapot</span> method.
        </p>
        <source>
public RegionBSPTree3D buildTeapot() {
    // build parts
    RegionBSPTree3D body = buildBody();

    // combine into the final product
    RegionBSPTree3D teapot = RegionBSPTree3D.empty();
    teapot.union(body);

    return teapot;
}

private RegionBSPTree3D buildBody() {
    // TODO
    return RegionBSPTree3D.empty();
}</source>
        <p>
        You'll notice that we've also started using one of the boolean operations mentioned earlier: <code>union</code>.
        The line <code>teapot.union(body)</code> computes the union of the <code>teapot</code>
        BSP tree with the <code>body</code> BSP tree and stores the result back into the caller, <code>teapot</code>.
        This is how we will merge all of the parts of our teapot into a single 3D region. Now, let's start building
        the body.
        </p>
        <p>
        Unlike some fancier models, our teapot is going to have a simple, rounded body. We will start by creating a sphere
        and go from there. Luckily, <em>Commons Geometry</em> provides a 
        <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/threed/shape/Sphere.html">Sphere</a>
        class to help us.
        </p>
        <source>
Sphere sphere = Sphere.from(Vector3D.ZERO, 1, precision);</source>
        <p>
        We now have a <code>Sphere</code> instance centered on the origin with a radius of <var>1</var>. However, our
        instance represents an analytic sphere, meaning it is does not contain any flat surfaces. This is great for
        many use cases, but we need flat surfaces in order to construct a BSP tree for our region. To convert
        from our mathematically perfect sphere abstraction to a BSP tree sphere approximation, we will use the 
        <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/threed/shape/Sphere.html#toTree">Sphere.toTree()</a>
        method. This method accepts a single argument that determines the number of facets that will be used in the approximation.
        The documentation explains the details of the conversion. For our purposes, we will use the argument <var>4</var>, which
        will give us a BSP tree with <var>2048</var> facets.
        </p>
        <source>
Sphere sphere = Sphere.from(Vector3D.ZERO, 1, precision);
RegionBSPTree3D body = sphere.toTree(4);</source>
        <p>
        This finally gives us something we can look at in our 3D modeling program.
        </p>
        <img src="../images/tutorials/teapot/sphere.png" />
        <p>
        Our next step is to tweak the sphere to make it more teapot-like. First, we will squash it vertically a little
        to make it less of a perfect sphere. Our tool of choice for this squashing exercise is the 
        <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/euclidean/threed/AffineTransformMatrix3D.html">AffineTransformMatrix3D</a>
        class, which we will be using quite frequently in the remainder of this tutorial.
        This class represents a 4x4 transform matrix that can be used to perform
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affine_transformation">affine transformations</a> in 3D space. In short,
        it lets us perform operations like translate, scale, and rotate on geometries. Here, we will use it to scale
        down our sphere approximation along the z-axis, while keeping the x and y scales the same.
        </p>
        <source>
AffineTransformMatrix3D t = AffineTransformMatrix3D.createScale(1, 1, 0.75);
body.transform(t);</source>
        <p>
        Our sphere now looks flattened a bit.
        </p>
        <img src="../images/tutorials/teapot/sphere-flattened.png" />
        <p>
        Note that our choice to scale along the z-axis (as opposed to the x or y axes) was completely arbitrary; our 
        sphere was entirely symmetrical and we had no definition of what was "up" and what was "down" for our teapot. 
        Now that we have performed our first non-symmetrical operation, we should officially declare the 
        orientation of our teapot: henceforth the positive z-axis will be "up" and the the positive x-axis will be 
        "forward" (the direction that the spout is pointing) in teapot-space. Keeping this orientation in mind 
        will help us when working through later transformations.
        </p>
        <p>
        Our teapot is now pleasantly flattened but it is still very likely to roll off tables and create all manner 
        of messes. To solve this shortcoming, we will chop off part of the bottom to make a flat base for the teapot
        to sit on. Another way to picture this is that we want to remove the part of the body that lies below a certain
        plane. As such, we can define this plane, construct a region of infinite size with that plane as the "top", 
        and compute the difference between our flattened sphere and the infinite region.   
        </p>
        <source>
Plane bottomPlane = Planes.fromPointAndNormal(
        Vector3D.of(0, 0, -0.6),
        Vector3D.Unit.PLUS_Z,
        precision);
PlaneConvexSubset bottom = bottomPlane.span();
body.difference(RegionBSPTree3D.from(Arrays.asList(bottom)));</source>
        <p>
        There's a lot going on in just a few lines there so let's go through it step by step.
        </p>
        <source>
Plane bottomPlane = Planes.fromPointAndNormal(
        Vector3D.of(0, 0, -0.6),
        Vector3D.Unit.PLUS_Z,
        precision);</source>
        <p>
        Here we construct our plane from a point lying in the plane, the plane normal, and our ever-present
        <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-core/apidocs/org/apache/commons/geometry/core/precision/DoublePrecisionContext.html">DoublePrecisionContext</a>.
        We chose a point that is directly "below" the origin per our previous definition of the teapot orientation and
        thus will intersect the bottom of the teapot. The normal points "up", along the positive z axis. 
        </p>
        <source>
PlaneConvexSubset bottom = bottomPlane.span();</source>
        <p>
        This may well be the most confusing line in this section. This line constructs a 
        <a class="code" href="../commons-geometry-euclidean/apidocs/org/apache/commons.geometry/euclidean/threed/PlaneConvexSubset.html">PlaneConvexSubset</a>
        that represents all of the points lying in the plane we created just before. These seem like equivalent concepts 
        but they're slightly different. The plane can be pictured as a container defining what points are available, while
        the convex subset selects a convex group of those points. Convex subsets include triangles, convex polygons,
        half-spaces, and, as in this case, every single last point in the entire plane (i.e., the "span").
        
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>